Finding Aid for Russell V. Judson Papers, 1913-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Russell V. Judson Papers 1913-1975
Judson, Russell V.
2 linear feet
85220 Aa 2
Linden, Genesee County, Michigan, businessman and inventor. Papers and photographs largely concerning agricultural and motion picture business interests, especially the Judson Michibean Company and the Photometric Products Corporation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Russell V. Judson (donor no. 5634 ) and came to the library in 1974-1975 with an addition in 1977.
The collection is open to research.
The Judson family was heavily involved in the agricultural and business life of lower Genesee County. In 1839 George Judson built a flour mill near what is today Fenton, Michigan. His son Ephraim, father of Russell V. Judson, later started several grain elevators in Michigan in partnership with his brothers; and in 1915, Russell Judson purchased an elevator from his father and began to experiment with new methods of handling grain and beans. Beginning in 1917, Judson developed several new machines for sorting beans. This machinery was later developed and marketed through the "Judson Michibean Company."
Russell Judson was also involved in an early motion picture equipment company, "Photometric Products Corporation" established in 1919 as a result of his investigation of the possible uses of photoelectric cells in bean sorting equipment. The Photometric Products Corporation made early efforts to perfect and commercially market selenium photoelectric cells. From this and related research came the technology that resulted in the first sound feature length motion picture in 1926. Besides P.P.C., several individuals and firms had also developed their own photoelectric development, and there was consequently a good deal of confusion over patent rights and royalties. In 1931, after lengthy investigation, Judson became convinced that the company's patent rights for motion picture sound development had been mishandled. He spent several years gathering evidence and, in 1939, he convinced the stockholders of the company to appoint him trustee in charge of advancing the company's claim to patent rights over the development of motion picture sound. A long legal battle began in 1940 and continued through the 1953 district court case.
The Judson collection could be of interest to researchers concerned with the technical development of American agriculture, especially beans, and for those interested in the motion picture industry. Among the papers are patents, technical information, and advertising releases on the development of Judson's mechanized agricultural equipment. This material documents the impact Judson's innovations had on the bean industry. There are also business papers of Ephraim and Russell Judson, which though incomplete, include several suits and financial reports of Judson's companies and features breakdowns on manufacturing and marketing costs for specific years. Also included is a scrapbook and a photo album of Judson's Michibean Company. Donated with the collection and separately cataloged are several issues of the Michigan bean industry publication "The Bean Bag."
Most of the material in the collection which relates to Photometric Products Corporation is legal in nature, and includes evidence and exhibits assembled for the 1953 lawsuit over the motion picture sound development patents. For the most part, the papers concern matters of ownership and patent rights, but some financial and technical information is also included. This material could be very useful in researching the technical development of film or in completing the legal history of the motion picture industry. However, it would need to be supplemented by the court records and evidence submitted by the other parties involved in the controversy.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical material; Business papers (mainly Michibean Company); Photometric Products Corporation materials; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Agricultural machinery.; Agriculture.; Beans.; Genesee County (Mich.); Judson, Russel V.; Judson Michibean Company.; Linden (Mich.); Motion picture industry.; Photometric Products Corporation.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural machinery.; Cemeteries--Michigan.; Christmas.; Durand (Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Linden.; Fenton, Lake (Mich.); Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Judson, Russell V.; Judson family.; Judson Michibean Company.; Laborers.; Linden (Mich.)--1900-1925.; Linden (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Railroad stations.; University Hall (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- Biographical material
  - Family and business information (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1)
- Business papers (mainly Michibean Company)
  - 1913 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918-1935, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - 1938, 1944, 1952, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with American consulates concerning overseas business expansion 1925 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Gill concerning lawsuit, Michigbean Growers Exchange vs. New Mexico Bean Pool 1931 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with George C. Jewett concerning business litigation 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Advertising and news stories, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Business papers; include financial analysis and manufacturing costs, ca. 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Business papers; include audits and financial statements 1933-1934, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lawsuit of Grain Processors Corp. against the Colorado Bean Growers Association 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - Credit rating report of Colorado Bean Growers Association 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of Judson Company business activities (Box 1)
- Photometric Products Corporation
  - Miscellaneous, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Notebook containing exhibits in the case of Photometric Products Corporation and Russell Judson vs. Albert A. Radtke 1954 (Box 2)
  - Scientific journals relating to inventions, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    (volumes perhaps maintained by J. D. Van Valkenburgh)
- Miscellaneous
  - Journal of trip to Europe; including essay on the use of motion pictures to educate immigrants aboard ocean liners 1913 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence of Beulah Bradley Judson (Box 2)
  - Correspondence concerning campaign of Mrs. Beulah Judson to be appointed to the Department of Labor and Industry 1932, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Essays of Rose and Ephraim Judson (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Home interiors (Box 2)
  - Judson with wife ? and in front of home (Box 2)
  - Judson Company, 1 envelope of loose photographs; 1 notebook (Box 2)
    (include agricultural equipment)
  - Lake views (Box 2)
  - Linden, Mich. (views, personalities, buildings (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (include train station, buildings, etc.) (Box 2)